A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18 FA290
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
1918-2003
Rockefeller Archive Center
Harkness, Edward Stephen
Commonwealth Fund
Harkness, Anna M. Richardson
Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman
Harkness, Charles W.
FA290
584.59 Cubic Feet 526 boxes and 529 microflim reels
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
Series 18 is divided into four subseries. Each series represents an additional accession of grant files.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Scope and Contents note
Grant actions comprise the largest series of the Commonwealth Fund records. The earliest grants funded a broad range of projects and associations and reflected the diverse and varied program of the Fund's beginning years. In many cases the grants were parallel or ancillary to existing Commonwealth Fund projects. Often, however, unrelated or special short-term grants were awarded. When the Commonwealth Fund's program became more oriented toward medical education and research, the grant actions mirrored this policy alteration. The records found in the Grants Series are the combination of the unprocessed Grants and Expired Grants Series.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Law; Legal issues; Legal research; Medical education; Medical research; Medicine, Rural; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Mental health; Child mental health; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Public health; Hygiene; Education, Rural; Child welfare; Child psychology; Public welfare; United States; War relief; Harvard University; Harkness, Edward Stephen; Social Science Research Council; Commonwealth Fund; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Columbia University; Yale University; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Phillips Exeter Academy; Harkness, Charles W.
- Grants, 1; 171.6 Cubic Feet; 390 boxes, 532 microfilm reels
  Arrangement note
  This subseries of records is arranged alphabetically by grant recipient.
  Scope and Contents note
  Grant actions comprise the largest series of the Commonwealth Fund records. The earliest grants funded a broad range of projects and associations and reflected the diverse and varied program of the Fund's beginning years. In many cases the grants were parallel or ancillary to existing Commonwealth Fund projects. Often, however, unrelated or special short-term grants were awarded. When the Commonwealth Fund's program became more oriented toward medical education and research, the grant actions mirrored this policy alteration. The records found in the Grant Series are the combination of the unprocessed Grants and Expired Grants Series.
  - Academy of Religion and Mental Health - Inter-Professional Education in Health Affairs (ME&CH), 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academy of Religion and Mental Health - Inter-Professional Education in Health Affairs (ME&CH), 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aid to Medical Schools in Underdeveloped Areas (ME&CH), 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also CF Series Advanced Medical Fellowships, Sub-Series Institutional Block Grants.
  - University of Alabama (Medical School) - Physiological Studies of Children with Congenital Heart Defects (MR), 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Original Grant to Johns Hopkins University.
  - University of Alabama (Medical School) - Physiological Studies of Children with Congenital Heart Defects - Financial Data (MR), 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - University of Alabama (Medical School) - Physiological Studies of the Heart and Circulation (MR), 1947-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - University of Alabama (Medical School) - Physiological Studies of the Heart and Circulation (MR), 1947-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - University of Alabama (Medical School) - Physiological Studies of the Heart and Circulation (MR), 1947-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - University of Alabama (Medical School) - Physiological Studies of the Heart and Circulation - Financial Data (MR), 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Albany Medical College-Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute - Integrated Program of Pre-Medical and Medical Education (ME&CH), 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Albany Medical College-Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute - Integrated Program of Pre-Medical and Medical Education (ME&CH), 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Albany Medical College-Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute - Integrated Program of Pre-Medical and Medical Education (ME&CH), 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Albany Medical College-Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute - Integrated Program of Pre-Medical and Medical Education (ME&CH), 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Albany Medical College-Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute - Integrated Program of Pre-Medical and Medical Education (ME&CH), 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - University of Alberta (Faculty of Medicine) - Extension of School Program into the Community, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Alderson-Broaddus College - Baccalaureate Program to Train Physicians Assistants (ME&CH), 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Alderson-Broaddus College - Baccalaureate Program to Train Physicians Assistants (ME&CH), 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Alderson-Broaddus College - Baccalaureate Program to Train Physicians Assistants (ME&CH), 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Alderson-Broaddus College - Baccalaureate Program to Train Physicians Assistants (ME&CH), 1969-1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Alderson-Broaddus College - Baccalaureate Program to Train Physicians Assistants (ME&CH), 1969-1977 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Alderson-Broaddus College - Baccalaureate Program to Train Physicians Assistants (ME&CH), 1969-1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Alderson-Broaddus College - Baccalaureate Program to Train Physicians Assistants (ME&CH), 1969-1977 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Alderson-Broaddus College - Baccalaureate Program to Train Physicians Assistants (ME&CH), 1969-1977 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Alderson-Broaddus College - Baccalaureate Program to Train Physicians Assistants (ME&CH), 1969-1977 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Alderson-Broaddus College - Baccalaureate Program to Train Physicians Assistants (ME&CH), 1969-1977 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Allen, Sylvia, 1927-1929 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences - Correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences - Developing a National Board for Peer Review of Physician Care, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences - Developing a National Board for Peer Review of Physician Care, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences - International Center for Insect Physiology and Ecology Nairobi, Kenya, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences - Occasional Bibliographic Review #1 ("History of Biochemistry in Japan 1877-1940: A Review of the Literature"), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences - Survey of Sources for History of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology; Archival Source Report #7 ("The Erwin Chargaff Papers"), 1977 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences - Survey of Sources Newsletter, 1975-1979 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - American Academy of Child Psychiatry - Study of the Needs of Mentally Ill Children and Adolescents and Implications for Training and Practice of Child Psychiatrists (Project Future), 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - American Academy of Child Psychiatry - Study of the Needs of Mentally Ill Children and Adolescents and Implications for Training and Practice of Child Psychiatrists (Project Future), 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - American Academy of Pediatrics - Study of Child Health in the United States, 1968-1977 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - American Arbitration Association - Application of Arbitration Procedures to Malpractice Disputes in the Health Field, 1974-1977; January 25, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - American Arbitration Association - Application of Arbitration Procedures to Malpractice Disputes in the Health Field, 1974-1977; January 25, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - American Arbitration Association - Consumers Systems and Organizations Providing Medical Services and Health Care, 1979-1982 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - American Arbitration Association - Test and Evaluation of the Role of Conflict Prevention and Resolution Procedures for the Health Care Field, 1973-1975; April 8, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - American Arbitration Association - Test and Evaluation of the Role of Conflict Prevention and Resolution Procedures for the Health Care Field (Health Service Associate), 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - Annual Meeting (January 26-31, 1975), 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - First General Meeting on Science and Technology (Science and Man in the Americas), 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - Symposium on Genetics, Man and Society, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - Systematic Plan for Medical Science Education, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - Television Programs/Annual Meeting, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - Television Programs/Annual Meeting, 1970-1974 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - American Association of Colleges of Pharmacy - Independent National Study Commission on Pharmacy, 1972-1976 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - American Association of Junior Colleges - Coordination of Community College and University Resources to Improve Allied Health Education, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - American Association of Junior Colleges - Coordination of Community College and University Resources to Improve Allied Health Education - "Conference Proceedings: New Directions in Post-Secondary Education Expanding Opportunities for the Occupational Education Student", May 10-11, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - American Association of Junior Colleges - Coordination of Community College and University Resources to Improve Allied Health Education - "Conference Proceedings: Whither Education for Health Care Delivery, A Florida Approach", May 3-4, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - American Association of Junior Colleges - Coordination of Community College and University Resources to Improve Allied Health Education - "Report: Interface The Universities and the Community Colleges Examine and Discuss the Issue, Concerns, and Future of Allied Health Education Programs Together", 1973 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - American Association of Psychiatric Social Workers, 1930-1934 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - American Association of Social Workers, 1919-1921 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - American Bar Association Fund for Public Education - Commission on Medical Professional Liability, 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - American Bar Association Fund for Public Education - Commission on Medical Professional Liability, 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - American Bible Society, April-October, 1919 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - American Blood Commission - Improved Management of National Blood Resources, 1975-1979 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - American Board of Pediatrics - Redefinition of Competent Pediatrician-Basis for Improved Certification Procedures in Pediatrics and Related Areas, 1972-1975 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - American Board of Pediatrics - Redefinition of Competent Pediatrician - Basis for Improved Certification Procedures in Pediatrics and Related Areas, 1972-1975 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - American Child Hygiene Association, 1920-1925 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - American City Bureau, May-October, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - American Classical League, 1922, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - American College Health Association - Fifth National Conference on Health in College Communities, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - American College Health Association - Study of the Role of College and University Health Programs-Health Service Delivery, 1972-1974 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - American College of Nurse-Midwives Foundation (Congress Fund) - 16th International Congress of Midwives, 1971-1974 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - American College of Surgeons - Diagnostic Clinics, February-June, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - American Committee on Armenian and Syrian Relief, April-May, 1919 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - American Conference on Hospital Service, 1925-1929 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - American Council on Education - "Conference: Presidents and Medical Education (May 6-7, 1978)", 1978-1979 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - American Ditchley Foundation - Anglo-American Conference on Psychiatry and the Law (November 5-8, 1971), 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - American Ditchley Foundation - Ditchley Conference on Health Services (December 8-11, 1972), 1972-1975 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - American Ditchley Foundation - Ditchley Conference on Health Services (December 8-11, 1972), 1972-1975 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - American Forestry Association, 1927-1932 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - American Forestry Association, 1927-1932 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - American Forestry Association, 1927-1932 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - American Forestry Association, 1927-1932 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - American Forestry Association, 1927-1932 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - American Friends Service - Medical Equipment Purchase Viet Duc Hospital, Hanoi, 1979-1980 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - American Hospital of Paris - Department of Eye Surgery, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - American Institute of Architects - Educational Facilities Laboratories, Inc. - Planning and Use of Ambulatory Care Facilities, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - American Institute of Architects - Educational Facilities Laboratories, Inc. - Planning and Use of Ambulatory Care Facilities, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - American Institute of Architects - Educational Facilities Laboratories, Inc. - Planning and Use of Ambulatory Care Facilities, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - American Institute of Architects - Proposal to Establish Health Facilities Research, Inc., February-September, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - American Land Service, July-August, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - American Law Institute - International Bill of Rights, 1942-1944 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - American Law Institute - Preparation of a Model Law Plan for Handling Delinquent Minors, 1938-1940 (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - American Law Institute - Youth Authority Program, April-June, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - American Liver Foundation - Support for Initial Development Programs, 1978-1981 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - American Medical Association - Education and Research Foundation - Loan Program to Help Minority Group Students to Complete Medical School, 1971-1981 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - American Medical Association - Education and Research Foundation - Loan Program to Help Minority Group Students to Complete Medical School, 1971-1981 (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - American Mission to Lepers, 1919-1936 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - American Museum of Natural History - Anthropology Collection Management Program, 1979-1983 (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - American Museum of Natural History - Centennial Campaign, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - American National Red Cross - Study of Joint Committee of the International Committee of Red Cross - Reappraisal of Role, 1974-1977 (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - American National Red Cross - Study of Joint Committee of the International Committee of Red Cross - Reappraisal of Role, 1974-1977 (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - American Psychiatric Association - Experimental Program for Working Committees, 1949-1952 (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - American Psychiatric Association - Experimental Program for Working Committees, 1949-1952 (Box 10, Folder 98)
  - American Psychiatric Association - Mental Hospital Service, 1948-1952 (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - American Psychiatric Association - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Mental Health Conference, 1971-1973 (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - American Public Health Association - Committee on Local Health Units, 1943-1946 (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - American Public Health Association - Educational Campaign, December 4, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - American Public Health Association - General Budget and Financial Data, 1932-1936 (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - American Public Health Association (Box 10, Folder 104)
    Personnel and Recruiting Service - August 16, 1926-October 22, 1926 "Popular Health Magazine" - December 13, 1919-January 20, 1920
  - American Public Health Association - Revision of Evaluation Methods, 1942-1943; November 14-29, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - American Public Health Association - State Health Studies, March-June, 1937; 1939-1947 (Box 11, Folder 106)
  - American Public Health Association - State Health Studies, March-June, 1937; 1939-1947 (Box 11, Folder 107)
  - American Public Health Association - State Health Studies, March-June, 1937; 1939-1947 (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - American Public Health Association - State Health Studies, March-June, 1937; 1939-1947 (Box 11, Folder 109)
  - American Public Health Association - State Health Studies, March-June, 1937; 1939-1947 (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - American Public Health Association - State Health Studies - Financial Data, 1937-1947 (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - American Public Health Association - State Health Studies - Financial Data, 1937-1947 (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - American Public Health Association - Study of Effectiveness of Administrative Health Practices, 1927-1935 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - American Public Health Association - Study of Effectiveness of Administrative Health Practices - "Report of the Subcommittee on Evaluation of Administrative Practices for the Year 1931 and Program for 1932" (Box 12, Folder 114)
  - American Public Health Association - Study of Effectiveness of Administrative Health Practices - "Scarlet Fever Studies 1927-1933" (Box 12, Folder 115)
  - American Red Cross (Box 12, Folder 116)
    Balkans Relief - June 9, 1919-July 30, 1919 Chilean Disaster Relief - June 14, 1960-June 16, 1960 Flood Relief - January 27, 1937 and August 23, 1955-November 17, 1955 Miscellaneous Grants - January 3, 1922 Russian Refugees - December 13, 1919-April 24, 1920 West Indies Hurricane Relief Fund - October 10, 1928
  - American Red Cross in Greater New York - Emergency Disaster Fund (Hurricane Agnes), October-December, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 117)
  - American Red Cross-New York Chapter - Harry Davison Fund, July 6, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 118)
  - American Relief Administration (Box 12, Folder 119)
    European Children's Fund - October 2, 1919-December 7, 1920 European Relief Council - October 5, 1920-May 11, 1921 Food Drafts for Intellectual Class in Central Europe - June 10, 1920-June 25, 1921
  - American Relief Administration - Relief of Intellectuals in Central Europe, 1920-1922 (Box 12, Folder 120)
    Five Grants.
  - American Relief Administration - Reports, 1920-1922 (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - American Social Hygiene Association, 1919-1922 (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - American Society for the Control of Cancer, 1919-1929 (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - American Society for the Control of Cancer, 1919-1929 (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - American Society of Law and Medicine/American Bar Association - "Current Status and Utility of American Emergency Medical Care Liability Law", 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - American Surgical Association and American College of Surgeons - Study of Surgical Services in the United States (SOSSUS), 1970-1977 (Box 13, Folder 126)